<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Packet Disarray]]></title>
  <link href="blog.packetdisarray.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="blog.packetdisarray.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-12T23:19:35-08:00</updated>
  <id>blog.packetdisarray.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bethany Long]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simplicity]]></title>
    <link href="blog.packetdisarray.com/2013/05/25/simplicity/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-25T17:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>blog.packetdisarray.com/2013/05/25/simplicity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s a feeling that gets in your bones, and doesn&rsquo;t get out. Like arsenic. And
lead.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Time]]></title>
    <link href="blog.packetdisarray.com/2013/01/15/time/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T22:16:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>blog.packetdisarray.com/2013/01/15/time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If the way we spend our time is the surest indication of who we are, then my
calling in life must be fruit fly genocide. Now, I&rsquo;m no sadist. I&rsquo;m not evil. My
hat is whiter than my ancestors&#8217; preferred subterranean source of dietary
starch. Whatever I&rsquo;m doing, though, the pests always make their way over for
some target practice, and I oblige with canny ruthlessness.</p>

<p>Recently I had to make the transition from working full-time over winter break
to working less than half-time as school has started up again. Since that
change, my working time has been increasingly besieged by meetings and other
such mundane affairs. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with them in themselves, but they
have a way of grinding up my time into crumbs when what I need are loaves.
Doubling the amount of time I can continuously work on something (within reason)
tends to increase my productivity by a factor considerably higher than two.</p>

<p>What with everything else I have going on in my life right now, it can be
tempting to resign myself to the tasks that more resemble flyswatting than
matters of actual significance (which, unfortunately for my metaphor, can
include actually resolving bugs). Satsifying though it may be to see the
entrails of small, bothersome insects splayed across my palms, the figurative
fruit flies that life sends my way can rarely be dispatched with such abandon.
The things I consider to be tedious annoyances may well be perceived differently
by others, and it would do me well to find the good in these things before
writing them off as time forever lost.</p>

<p>Or something like that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
